A Finding Aid to the Lilian Swann Saarinen Papers, 1920-1977, in the Archives of American Art AAA.saarlili
Archives of American Art
Lilian Swann Saarinen papers
1920-1977
AAA.saarlili
Archives of American Art
9.4 Linear feet
The papers of Cambridge sculptor and illustrator, Lilian Swann Saarinen, measure 9.4 linear feet and date from 1920 to 1977. The collection documents Saarinen's career through correspondence with artists, architects, publishers, and gallery owners; writings and notes, including manuscripts and illustrations for children's books and publications; project and teaching files; financial records; artwork including numerous project sketches; and photos of Saarinen and her artwork. Saarinen's personal life is also documented through diaries and correspondence with friends and family members including Eero Saarinen, to whom she was married from 1939-1953.
Saarinen, Lilian Swann, 1912-1995
Arrangement note
The collection is arranged as 11 series.
Series 1: Biographical Material, circa 1930s-1960s (3 folders; Box 1, OV 12)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1920-1974 (2 linear feet; Boxes 1-2, 8, OV 12)
Series 3: Writings and Notes, 1920s-1973 (1.3 linear feet, Boxes 2-3, 8, OVs 13-15, 19)
Series 4: Diaries, 1930-1973 (1.5 linear feet, Boxes 3-5, 8)
Series 5: Project Files, 1931-1966 (1.8 linear feet, Boxes 5-6, 8, OVs 20-23)
Series 6: Teaching Files, 1966-1970 (3 folders, Box 6)
Series 7: Financial Records, 1940s-1970s (2 folders, Box 6)
Series 8: Printed Material, circa 1930s-1970s (0.2 linear feet, Box 6)
Series 9: Scrapbooks, circa 1909-1974 (2 folders; Boxes 6, 9)
Series 10: Artwork, circa 1920s-circa 1960s (2.1 linear feet, Boxes 6-7, 9-10, OVs 17-18, 24-31)
Series 11: Photographs, circa 1940s, 1977 (0.5 linear feet, Boxes 7, 11, OV 25)
Conditions Governing Access note
Use of original papers requires an appointment and is limited to the Archives’ Washington, D.C. Research Center. Contact Reference Services for more information.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The papers were donated by Lilian Swann Saarinen in 1975.
Separated Materials note
Also in the Archives are materials loaned for microfilming by Saarinen in 1976, including a scrapbook containing clippings, copies of letters and telegrams received, and reproductions of Saarinen's work; a copy of Saarinen's book, Who Am I?; and 3 albums containing photographs of Saarinen, photographs and reproductions of her work, a list of exhibitions, quotes about her, and writings by her about sculpture.
Loaned material is available on reels 1152 and 1192, but is not described in the Container Listing of this finding aid.
Scope and Contents note
The papers of Cambridge sculptor and illustrator, Lilian Swann Saarinen, measure 9.4 linear feet and date from 1920 to 1977. The collection documents Saarinen's career through correspondence with artists, architects, publishers, and gallery owners; writings and notes, including manuscripts and illustrations for children's books and publications; project and teaching files; financial records; artwork including numerous project sketches; and photos of Saarinen and her artwork. Saarinen's personal life is also documented through diaries and correspondence with friends and family members including Eero Saarinen, to whom she was married from 1939-1953.
Biographical material consists of resumes and biographical sketches, as well as a 1951 blueprint for the Eero Saarinen and Associates Office Building in Bloomfield Hills, Michigan.
Correspondence documents Saarinen's personal and professional life through letters to and from Eero Saarinen and other family members including 6 letters from Loja Saarinen, correspondence with artists and architects including Merle Armitage, Charles and Ray Eames, Carl Koch, Henry Kreis, Carl Milles, Laszlo and Sibyl Moholy-Nagy, Robert Venturi and Harry Weese; and friends and colleagues at the Cranbrook Academy of Art and Knoll Associates. Also documented is Saarinen's business relationship with Midtown Galleries and Caresse Crosby, and publishers and publications including Child Life, Interiors, Otava Publishing Company, and Reynal & Hitchcock, Inc.
Writings and Notes document Saarinen's work on several children's publications, including Picture Book Zoo (1935) and Who Am I? (1946), through correspondence, notes, manuscript drafts and extensive sketches. This series also includes Saarinen's ideas for other publications and incorporates some early writings and notes, as well as typescripts of her reminiscences about Eliel Saarinen, the Saarinen family, and the Cranbrook Academy of Art.
Diaries consist of bound diary volumes, loose-leaf journal entries, and heavily annotated engagement calendars, documenting Saarinen's personal life, artistic aspirations and developing career from the 1930s-1970s. They provide an in-depth view into the emotional landscape of Saarinen's life and her relationship with the internationally renowned architectural family into which she married.
Project files document Saarinen's work on book cover designs, federal and post office commissions in Bloomfield, Indiana, Carlisle, Kentucky, and Evanston, Illinois, reliefs for the Crow Island School in Winnetka, Illinois, and other important commissions including the Harbor National Bank Clock in Boston, Massachusetts, the KLM Airlines installation at JFK Airport, the Fountain of Noah sculpture at the Northland Center in Detroit, Michigan and the interior of Toffenetti's restuarant in Chicago, Illinois. Also documented is her role in designs for the Gateway Arch in St. Louis, with Eero Saarinen.
Teaching files document Saarinen's "Language of Clay Course" which she taught at Cambridge Art Center and the Massachusetts Institute of Technology.
Financial records document exhibition and sales expenses for two exhibitions, including her show at G Place Gallery in 1944.
Printed material consists of clippings about Saarinen and her family, exhibition announcements and catalogs for herself and others, and source files from the 1930s-1940s, primarily comprising clippings of animals.
Additional printed material documenting Saarinen's career can be found in one of two scrapbooks found in the collection. An additional scrapbook consists of clippings relating primarily to Saarinen's parents.
Artwork comprises extensive sketches, particularly animal and figure sketches, in pencil, crayon, ink, pastel and watercolor. The sketches demonstrate in particular Saarinen's developing interest in and skill with animal portraiture from her childhood to the 1960s.
Photographs are primarily of artwork and Saarinen's 1944 exhibition at G Place Gallery. Also found are 1 negative of Saarinen, probably with Eero Saarinen, and a group photo including Lilian, Eero and Eliel Saarinen with the model for the Detroit Civic Center, circa 1940s.
Biographical/Historical note
Cambridge artist and sculptor, Lilian Swann Saarinen (1912-1995), studied at the Art Students League with Alexander Archipenko in 1928, and later with Albert Stewart and Heninz Warneke from 1934-1936, before moving to Michigan where she studied with Carl Milles at the Cranbrook Academy of Art from 1936-1940. Saarinen was an accomplished skier and a member of the 1936 US Olympic ski team.
At Cranbrook Lilian Swann met architect Eero Saarinen whom she married in 1939. She subsequently worked with Saarinen's design group on a variety of projects including the Westward Expansion Memorial, which later became known as the "Gateway Arch" in St. Louis. They had a son, Eric, and a daughter, Susie, before divorcing in 1953.
Saarinen, who had developed an affinity for drawing animals in childhood, specialized in animal portraits in a variety of sculptural media. In 1939, she exhibited her sculpture Night, which depicted Bagheera the panther from Rudyard Kipling's Jungle Book, at the World's Fair. The sculpture was placed in the Boston Public Garden in 1986. In the 1930s and 1940s Saarinen was commissioned to work on a variety of architectural projects, including reliefs for post offices in Bloomfield, Indiana, Carlisle, Kentucky, and Evanston, Illinois, and the Crow Island School in Winnetka, Illinois. She also executed commissions for the Harbor National Bank in Boston, KLM (Royal Dutch Airlines) at JFK Airport, the Northland shopping Center in Detroit Michigan, and Toffenetti's Restaurant in Chicago.
Saarinen was a contributing author and illustrator for a variety of publications, including Child Life, Interiors and Portfolio: An Intercontinental Quarterly. In 1935 she illustrated Picture Book Zoo for the Bronx Zoo and in 1946 Reynal & Hitchcock, Inc. published Who Am I?, a children's book which Saarinen wrote and illustrated.
Saarinen taught ceramic sculpture to soldiers for the Red Cross Arts and Skills Unit rehabilitation program in 1945, served on the Visiting Committee to the Museum School at the Museum of Fine Arts, Boston from 1959-1964 where she taught ceramics, and later taught a course entitled "The Language of Clay" at the Cambridge Art Center and the Massachusetts Institute of Technology. One of Saarinen's private students at Cambridge was her cousin, Edie Sedgwick.
Saarinen died in Cohasset, Massachusetts in 1995 at the age of 83.
Armitage, Merle, 1893-1975; Cranbrook Academy of Art -- Faculty; Crosby, Caresse, 1892-; Eames, Charles; Eames, Ray; G Place Gallery (Washington, D.C.).; Knoll Associates, inc.; Kreis, Henry, 1899-1963; Massachusetts Institute of Technology. -- Faculty; Midtown Galleries (New York, N.Y.); Milles, Carl, 1875-1955; Moholy-Nagy, László, 1895-1946; Moholy-Nagy, Sibyl, 1905-; Reynal & Hitchcock.; Saarinen, Eero, 1910-1961; Saarinen, Eliel, 1873-1950; Saarinen, Loja; Venturi, Robert; Weese, Harry, 1915-1998; Animal painters; Art--Study and teaching; Blueprints; Diaries; Drawing; Drawings; Gateway Arch (Saint Louis, Mo.); Illustrated books, Children's; Illustrations; Illustrators--Massachusetts; Photographs; Sculptors--Massachusetts--Cambridge; Sculpture, Modern--20th century--United States; Sketches
- Biographical Material, circa 1930s-1960s; Series 1; 3 Folders Box 1, OV 12
  Scope and Contents note
  Biographical material consists of resumes and biographical sketches written by Saarinen, and a 1951 blueprint of the Eero Saarinen and Associates office building in Bloomfield Hills, Michigan, labeled "July/54 Kiln data."
  - Blueprint, Eero Saarinen and Associates Office Building, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Oversized material housed in OV 12
  - Resumes and Biographical Notes, circa 1930s-1960s (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Blueprint, Eero Saarinen and Associates Office Building from Box 1, Folder 1 (Box OV 12)
- Correspondence, 1920-1974; Series 2; 2 Linear feet Boxes 1-2, 8, OV 12
  Arrangement note
  Correspondence is arranged alphabetically. Correspondents who are represented by 4 or more items are housed in named files; all others are housed in general files for the corresponding letter of the alphabet.
  Sarrinen's correspondence files document her personal life and career. Personal correspondence includes letters written between Lilian and Eero Saarinen which provide insight into their relationship during the 1940s and early 1950s, and their decision to divorce in 1953. These letters also reference professional projects, including Eero Saarinen's involvement in the design of the Antioch College residence halls and his work on the UNESCO headquarters in Paris. The letters describe some of his planning meetings and enclose sketches of the UNESCO project.
  Many letters from Susan Hammond, Saarinen's mother, chronicle events in the Swann and Sedgwick families. Hammond frequently enclosed letters sent to her about her daughter in her letters to Lilian. Family correspondence includes letters from Saarinen's son, Eric, her sister Lucy Livingston Schwartz, letters from members of the Swann family, and a letter from her cousin, Edie Sedgwick.
  8 folders of corresondence document Saarinen's relationship with friend and frequent confidante, photographer Roxanne Lambie.
  Letters which document Saarinen's professional life include correspondence with publishers and publications such as Child Life, for which Saarinen provided illustrations; Interiors regarding the publication of an article by Saarinen about her and her work; Otava Publishing Company including the 1956 contract for the Finnish edition of Who Am I?; Reynal & Hitchcock, Inc., relating to the original publication of Who Am I? in 1946; and Rutgers University Press regarding Saarinen's proposed jacket design for the cover of A Short Chronology of American History 1492-1950 (1952) by Irving S. and Nell M. Kull. Additional correspondence relating to Saarinen's writings can be found in Series 3: Writings and Notes.
  Also found is correspondence with Caresse Crosby regarding the consignment of Saarinen's artwork to Gump's and other galleries in the 1940s, and referencing Crosby's Portfolio: An Intercontinental Quarterly for which Saarinen provided illustrations. Correspondence with Alan D. Gruskin of Midtown Galleries, who Saarinen contracted to represent her nationally from 1943-1948, includes Saarinen's sketches for her 1944 exhibition at G Place Gallery in Washington D. C., under the direction of Caresse Crosby.
  The series includes substantial correspondence with other artists and architects, many of whom were personal friends of Saarinen, including Merle Armitage, Walter Baermann, Alexander Calder, Charles and Ray Eames, Carl Koch, Henry Kreis, Carl Milles, Laszlo and Sibyl Moholy-Nagy, Robert Venturi, and Harry Weese. Also found is correspondence with the design firm Knoll Associates, Cranbrook Academy of Art directors and artists Soltan Sepeshy, Maija Grotell and Marianne Strengell, 6 letters from Loja Saarinen, and a telegram from Eliel Saarinen.
  The bulk of the correspondence relating to Saarinen's sculpture commissions can be found in Series 5: Project Files, but related correspondence is scattered throughout this series.
  - Abernathy, J.T., 1956-1964 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Arkell, John, 1938-1974 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Armitage, Merle and Elsa, 1942-1953 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - A, General, 1940s-1970s (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Baldinger, Wallace S., 1948-1949 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Bank of New York, 1946-1952 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Barns, Katrina McCormick, circa 1940s (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - B, General, 1930s-1970s (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Calder, Alexander, 1940-1955 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Cavin, W. Brooks Jr., 1947 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Child Life, 1946-1948 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Congratulations/Thank You Letters for Picture Book Zoo, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Cranbrook Academy of Art (Maija Grotell, Zoltan Sepeshy, Marianne Strengell), 1940s-1970 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Crosby, Caresse, 1934-1947 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - C, General, 1940s-1970s (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Danforth, Maija C., circa 1943-1972 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - D, General, 1930s-1970s (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Eames, Charles and Ray (Box 1, Folder 20)
    Includes illustrated letters; oversized material housed in Box 8, Folder 1
  - English, Miller & Hockett, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - E, General, 1940s-1950s (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Falch, Hedi, 1940-1947 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - F, General, 1930s-1970s (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Grandin, Isabella (Bella), 1960s-1972 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - G, General, 1940s-1970s (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Hallowell, Johnny and Sis, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Hammond, Susan and Paul, circa 1920s-circa 1970s (Box 1, Folder 28)
    One letter to Saarinen in this folder encloses photos of Lilian Swann Saarinen, circa 1935
  - Hammond, Susan and Paul, circa 1940-circa 1954 (Box 1, Folder 29-30)
  - Hammond, Susan and Paul, 1920-1974 (Box 1, Folder 31-39)
    Oversized material housed in Box 8, Folder 1
  - Haskell, Helen, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - H, General, 1930s-1970s (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Interiors, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - I, General, 1940s (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - J, General, 1940s-1950s (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Kiaer, Herman S, 1970s (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Kline, Robert and Norma, 1953-1954 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Knoll Associates, 1948-1954 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Koch, Carl, 1942-1947 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Kreis, Henry, 1940-1953 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - K, General, 1930s-1970s (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Lambie, Roxanne, circa 1940-1973 (Box 1, Folder 51-54)
  - Lambie, Roxanne, 1953-1974 (Box 2, Folder 1-3)
  - Lander, E. W., 1948 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Laughlin, James (Jay), circa 1939-1954 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Loth, David, 1943 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Lueders, J. E., circa 1940-1942 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Lutgerath, Hadwiga, 1947 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - L, General (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Midtown Galleries, circa 1941-1949 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Milles, Carl, 1943-1948 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Moholy-Nagy, Laszlo and Sibyl, 1945-1948 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Moloney, James Clark, 1966-1972 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Museum of Fine Arts, Boston, 1959-1964 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Museum of Modern Art, 1945-1949 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - M, General, 1940s-1970s (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Norton, Marthia, 1938-1972 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - N, General, 1930s-1940s (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Otava Publishing Company, 1955-1959 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - O, General, 1951-1952 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Perkins, Lawrence and Midge, 1940-1948 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Putnam, Brenda, 1934-1943 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - P, General, 1930s-1950s (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Rathbone, Beatrice (Babs), 1940s-1969 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Reynal & Hitchcock, Inc., 1945-1947 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Roach, Ellie (Ellie Worthyn), circa 1940s-1970 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Robinson, Maude, 1948-1959 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Root, Clark, Buckner & Ballantine, 1945-1948 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Rutgers University Press, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - R, General, 1930s-1970s (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Saarinen, Eero, circa 1940s-1950s (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Saarinen, Eero, 1939-1954 (Box 2, Folder 32-34)
  - Saarinen, Loja, 1940s-1950s (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Saunders, Louise and Silvia, 1940s-1950s (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Schwartz, Lucy Livingston, 1940s-1970 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Stewart, Albert and Margaret, 1933-circa 1940 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Syracuse Museum of Fine Arts, 1942-1949 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - S, General, 1930s-1970s (Box 2, Folder 40-41)
  - S, Illegible, 1940s-1970s (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Thank You Letters from Children for Who Am I?, 1946-1947 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - T, U, V, General, 1930s-1940s (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Venturi, Robert, 1953-1955 (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Weese, Harry, circa 1940-1955 (Box 2, Folder 46-47)
  - Weese, Harry E., 1953 (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Winnetka Public Schools, 1945-1946 (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - W, General, 1940s-1970s (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - Y-Z, General, 1942-1972 (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - First Names Only
    - Alice, Anna-Greta, 1940s-1950s (Box 2, Folder 52)
    - Barbara, Ben, Bobbie, 1940-1969 (Box 2, Folder 53)
    - Camilla, Casanova, Cavannas, Charles, Claus, circa 1940s-1971 (Box 2, Folder 54)
    - Dorothy, Doda, circa 1930s-1940s (Box 2, Folder 55)
      Doda letter encloses childhood drawings by Swann Saarinen
    - Ed, Fran, Fred, circa 1940-1952 (Box 2, Folder 56)
    - Gardner, Greta, Herman, Hildy, 1940s-1972 (Box 2, Folder 57)
    - Jack, Jean, Jeanne, Jessie, John, circa 1939-1970 (Box 2, Folder 58)
    - Kenneth, Kiki, Kim, Louise, circa 1931-1956 (Box 2, Folder 59)
    - Margaret, Marilyn, Marjorie, Marlee, Mary, circa 1941-1972 (Box 2, Folder 60)
    - Nell, Norma, Olga, 1934-1947 (Box 2, Folder 61)
    - Pamela, Peter, Poppy, 1930s-1970 (Box 2, Folder 62)
    - R, Illegible, Roland, S, Illegible, circa 1940s (Box 2, Folder 63)
    - T, Illegible, Tom, Val, William (Bill), Willy, circa 1940s-1950s (Box 2, Folder 64)
  - Fragments of Letters from Lily Swann Saarinen, circa 1930s-circa 1970s (Box 2, Folder 65)
  - Illegible/Unidentified, circa 1940s-1970s (Box 2, Folder 66)
  - Oversized Eames, Charles and Ray from Box 1, Folder 20 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Oversized Hammond, Susan and Paul from Box 1, Folders 31-39 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Oversized Saarinen, Eero from Box 2 Folders 31 and 33 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Oversized First Names Only, Barbara, Be, Bobbie, From Box 2, Folder 53 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Oversized First Names Only, Jack, Jean, Jeanne, Jessie, John from Box 2, Folder 58 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Oversized Cavin, W. Brooks Jr. from Box 1, Folder 12 (Box OV 12)
  - Oversized Koch, Carl From Box 1, Folder 48 (Box OV 12)
  - Oversized Midtown Galleries from Box 2, Folder 10 (Box OV 12)
- Writings and Notes, 1920s-1973; Series 3; 1.3 Linear feet Boxes 2-3, 8, OVs 13-15, 19
  Writings and notes document the writing and publication of Saarinen's Picture Book Zoo and Who Am I?, as well as Saarinen's ideas in draft, typescript and sketch form for other publications such as "Animals and War Machines," a proposed follow-up to Who Am I? entitled "Who Helps Who?" and other children's writings such as "Susie Sing All Day" and "What Is Mine?" Documentation consists of correspondence with publishers, drafts and typsecripts of texts, original artwork, photos of artwork, and book layouts.
  Also found are school writings from the 1920s-1930s, misellaneous notes and writings, and typescripts and handwritten drafts of Saarinen's memories of the Cranbrook Academy of Art, Eliel Saarinen, and the Saarinen family.
  - Anatomy Notebook, 1937 (Box 2, Folder 67)
  - "Animals and War Machines" Book Ideas, circa 1944 (Box 2, Folder 68-69)
  - "Animals and War Machines" Book Idea, Preliminary Sketches, circa 1944 (Box 2, Folder 70-73)
    Oversized material housed in Box 8, Folder 2 and OV 13
  - "Miscellaneous Secret Thoughts and Writings of Mine", 1929 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Miscellaneous Wrtings, 1930s-1940s (Box 3, Folder 2-3)
  - Notes, circa 1961-1970s (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Notes, Miscellaneous, 1930s-1970s (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Other Book Ideas, 1940s (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Picture Book Zoo
    - Artwork, 1938 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Sketches, Hippos, circa 1936 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Published Copy, 1935 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - "Quotations and Thoughts and Animal Records (in back) from Winter with Saunders", 1929-1930 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Reminiscences about Eliel Saarinen for Nancy Rivard, 1972-1973 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Reminiscences about the Saarinens and Cranbrook Art Academy, circa 1960s-1970s (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - School Writings, 1920s (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - "Susie Sing All Day", circa 1947 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    Oversized material housed in OV 14
  - "What is Mine?", 1947-1948 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Who Am I?
    - Correspondence, 1940s (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Notes, 1940s (Box 3, Folder 17-18)
    - Notes and Typescripts, 1940s (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Original Artwork, 1940s (Box 3, Folder 20)
      Oversized material housed in Box 8, Folder 3 and OV 19
    - Photographs of Artwork, 1940s (Box 3, Folder 21)
      Oversized material housed in OVs 13 and 15
    - Proof, circa 1946 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Sketches, 1940s (Box 3, Folder 23-25)
    - Sketches for Flyleaf, circa 1946 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - "Who Helps Who?"
    - Artwork, 1940s (Box 3, Folder 27-29)
    - Correspondence, 1946-1952 (Box 3, Folder 30)
    - Sketches and Notes, 1940s (Box 3, Folder 31-32)
  - Oversized "Animals and War Machines" Book Idea, Preliminary Sketches from Box 2, Folders 70-73 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Oversized Who Am I?, Original Artwork from Box 3, Folder 20 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Oversized "Animals and War Machines," Book Idea, Preliminary Sketches from Box 2, Folders 70-73 (Box OV 13)
  - Oversized Who Am I?, Photos of Artwork from Box 3, Folder 21 (Box OV 13)
  - Oversized "Susie Sing All Day" from Box 3, Folder 14 (Box OV 14)
  - Oversized Who Am I?, Photos of Artwork from Box 3, Folder 21 (Box OV 15)
  - Oversized Who Am I?, Original Artwork from Box 3, Folder 20 (Box OV 19)
- Diaries, 1930-1973; Series 4; 1.5 Linear feet Boxes 3-5, 8